<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: google | revolunet blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.revolunet.com/blog/categories/google/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.revolunet.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-13T02:26:55+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.revolunet.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[revolunet team]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[contact@revolunet.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[GoogleIO 2013 keynote recap]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.revolunet.com/blog/2013/05/15/google-io-2013-keynote/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-15T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.revolunet.com/blog/2013/05/15/google-io-2013-keynote</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So today was the opening of the 2013 GoogleIO developer conference in San Francisco and the Googlers announced a <strong>insanely crazy</strong> amount of new projects/services/features in just the first few hours, which is very exciting for every web/android developer. The next three days will be very busy, with a lot of focus on Chrome, Android and Google+.</p>

<p>Though, we don't have new Nexus devices, no Android 4.3, and no Javascript AppEngine runtime. So huge fail on my <a href="https://twitter.com/revolunet/status/333620420798472192">previous predictions</a>.</p>

<p>The keynote started with a big fail demo effect happened in the very first demo about Android multiplayer gaming when demoing a new Google Cloud Messaging feature, quite embarassing, but then everything ran smoothly.</p>

<p>Here's a little recap of the most important things announced just during the 3 hours keynote :</p>

<h2><a href="http://officialandroid.blogspot.fr/2013/05/androidio-just-press-play.html">Android</a></h2>

<ul>
<li>Google cloud messaging : can now be used in a bidirectionnal way, and apps can now also store data in the cloud and sync it across devices (scores, leaderboards...).</li>
<li>Google Game Services platform to help game developers with new APIs</li>
<li>Samsung Galaxy S4 will be available in June on Google Play with standard Android build and unlocked bootloader ! 649$ though but without that ugly, messy, shitty Samsung overlay.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=e0fXuyL0xVU">Android studio</a> to replace Eclipse nightmare, finally ! good move !</li>
<li>Unified and synced notifications between devices.</li>
<li>Translation service for apps, better analytics...</li>
<li>Enhanced maps API</li>
</ul>


<h2><a href="http://play.google.com/about/music/">Google Music</a></h2>

<ul>
<li>Access to all the music for 9.99$/month</li>
<li>Discover to new recommended songs with google suggestions</li>
<li>Google powered radio feature based on what you like</li>
</ul>


<h2><a href="https://plus.google.com/+chrome/posts">Chrome / Web</a></h2>

<ul>
<li>750 millions active chrome users globally</li>
<li>WebP and VP9 royalty-free compression standards for images and videos to increase speed specially on mobile devices.</li>
<li>Google provides a free (deactivable) proxy for Android to improve speed based on this codecs.</li>
<li>New payment autocomplete API will help process payments quickly on websites, specially useful on mobile (2 clicks payments)</li>
<li>Google will finally release a rock solid UI framework based on web components standards : <a href="http://www.polymer-project.org">polymer-project.org</a> . I wonder how it will fit with AngularJS.</li>
<li>V8 will integrate asm.js to improve Javascript performance.</li>
</ul>


<h2><a href="http://googleplusproject.blogspot.fr/2013/05/new-google-stream-hangouts-and-photos.html">Google +</a></h2>

<ul>
<li>New interface :)</li>
<li>Better Hangouts</li>
<li>Unified notifications across devices</li>
<li>Better pictures management, event an 'auto awesome' mode :)</li>
</ul>


<h2><a href="http://google-latlong.blogspot.fr/2013/05/meet-new-google-maps-map-for-every.html">Maps</a></h2>

<ul>
<li>iPad version this summer</li>
<li>Brand new Google maps, with new design, more space for content, and builtin 3D thanks to WebGL</li>
</ul>


<h2>Gmail</h2>

<ul>
<li>You can now <a href="http://googlecommerce.blogspot.fr/2013/05/send-money-to-friends-with-gmail-and.html">send money to your friends right from Gmail with google wallet</a> :)</li>
<li>Developers can now <a href="http://googleappsdeveloper.blogspot.fr/2013/05/introducing-actions-in-inbox-powered-by.html">add actions to their email</a></li>
</ul>


<h2>In other news</h2>

<ul>
<li>For some reasons (<a href="https://code.google.com/p/googleappengine/issues/list">top requested features</a>), <a href="https://gaeforphp.appspot.com">Google choosed PHP over Javascript as a new AppEngine runtime</a>. <strong>#WTF</strong></li>
<li>Google Play for education allows teachers/schools to push content directly to students devices</li>
<li>Google TVs will be <a href="https://plus.google.com/+GoogleTVDevelopers/posts/X5rmq6Yu8xG">updated to Android 4.2 and latest chrome</a> !</li>
</ul>


<p>Anything missed ?</p>

<p>You can still watch the full keynote <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lLPue2vK3wg">on Youtube</a> of course.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
